Guide to the Taxi Rank and File Coalition Oral History Collection OH.013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Taxi Rank and File Coalition Oral History Collection
1972 - circa 1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Taxi Rank and File Coalition
Gordon, John
Saltzer, Steve
Wasserman, Paul
OH.013
1 Linear Feet in 1 compact disk box and 1 audio cassette box
The Taxi Driver's Rank and File Coalition was organized on April 15, 1971 to advocate for fairer contracts and more democratic practices within the New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036. The union, led by Harry Van Arsdale, had a top-down structure, and proved unable to control the daily shape-ups that allowed company dispatchers to extort payoffs from drivers and discriminate against activists. Dissatisfaction with Van Arsdale's leadership style and the contracts that union leadership had negotiated led to electoral challenges from the Rank and File Coalition and wildcat strikes during the 1970s, with varying effectiveness. In July of 1977, the Rank and File Coalition failed to run a slate of candidates in the election and ceased publication of the rank and file paper, Hot Seat. Van Arsdale had removed himself from the union in 1973, and his successor Ben Goldberg presided over the merger of the Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union and the SEIU in 1978. The collection consists of thirty-six access compact disks, derived from twenty-three cassettes. Interviewees discuss working conditions, contract issues, racism, and what they perceived were the undemocratic practices of the Harry Van Arsdale leadership.
Conditions Governing Access
Materails are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated to the library by John Gordon, Steve Saltzer, and Paul Wasserman, date unknown. The accession number related to this gift is 1978.013.
Arrangement
Cassettes were assigned numbers when the collection was initially indexed, and this order has been maintained.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Taxi Driver's Rank and File Coalition was organized on April 15, 1971 to advocate for fairer contracts and more democratic practices within the New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036.
The Taxi Drivers Union was organized in the mid-1960s with the help of the Central Labor Council and its president Harry Van Arsdale. Van Arsdale imposed a top-down approach to union administration that many of the drivers resisted. Opposition built when the union proved unable to control the daily shape-ups that allowed company dispatchers to extort payoffs from drivers and discriminate against activists. When Van Arsdale agreed to a concessionary contract in 1971, a bitter strike ensued, and his staff was run out of a union meeting. A federal judge ordered the contract brought to a vote, and it was rejected 3 -1. Leasing was a major issue. It had been outlawed when the medallion system was established in the 1930s, but the new contract allowed it on a "voluntary" basis. After six months of conflict the owners declared an impasse and implemented the rejected contract. The union failed to respond and a wildcat strike at one garage quickly petered out. These failures and division undercut whatever strength the union had.
The taxi drivers who opposed Van Arsdale's leadership organized the Taxi Rank and File Coalition. They ran a full slate of candidates in the 1971 election and received forty-two percent of the vote. Van Arsdale won re-election, but with a plurality rather than majority. The coalition filed thirty-six counts of election-fraud with the Department of Labor.
In 1974, the Rank and File Coalition presented 2,500 signatures for the restoration of the committee elections. On May 14-15 of that year the coalition led a strike at the Dover Garage for unfair dismissals. After the dismissed were given back their jobs, the Rank and File fought the proposed fare hike of the Taxi Commission. After fighting all year for committee elections, the Rank and File received a favorable ruling in court. In June, the Rank and File won a substantial victory in the election, which was marred by irregularities; a new election was ordered.
By the July of 1977, driver interest in the Rank and File Coalition had declined. It failed to run a slate of candidates in the election and ceased publication of the rank and file paper, Hot Seat. Van Arsdale had removed himself from the union in 1973, and his successor Ben Goldberg presided over the merger of the Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union and the SEIU in 1978.
Related Materials
Taxi Rank and File Coalition Records (WAG.139)
New York City Taxi Drivers Union Oral History Collection (OH.028)
The Tamiment Library also holds issues of the Taxi Rank and File Coalition's newspaper, The Hot Seat.
Scope and Contents
The interviews of this collection were taken as part of an archival project organized by the Taxi Rank and File Coalition in the late 1970s and early 1980s. According to its guidelines, the purpose of the project was to compile an oral history of the New York taxi industry "as seen through the eyes of the taxi workers." Interviews were conducted by coalition members John Gordon and Paul Wasserman. The interviews were to support a never-completed book and radio program about the history of the Taxi Rank and File Coalition and experiences of drivers, including racism. Some interviews were conducted in 1976-1977 at Dover Garage, where a strike was taking place.
The collection consists of thirty-six access compact disks, and the twenty-three cassettes from which they were derived. Interviewees discuss working conditions, contract issues, and what they perceived were the undemocratic practices of the Harry Van Arsdale leadership. The collection includes group and individual interviews with rank and file activists and coalition leaders. The issues of race and intergenerational conflict are major themes. Of particular interest are group interviews entitled "Racism Sum Up" and "Black Drivers on Racism." There is a recording of a June 6, 1972 owner driver unity meeting.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Labor union democracy -- New York (State); Taxicab drivers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Racism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Taxicab drivers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Taxi Rank and File Coalition; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1905-1986; Gordon, John; Saltzer, Steve; Wasserman, Paul
- Bob Z, February 19, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 1)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 1)
- Gerri, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 2)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 2)
- Carol and Rich, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 3)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 3-4)
- Sam Lazarus, April 4, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 4)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 5)
- Steve S., undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 5)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 6-7)
- Mike Z., Kevin & John, May 4, 1978 - May 5, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 6)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 8-9)
- Larry Guineland, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 7)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 10-11)
- Phil and Larry G., undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 8)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 12)
- Bob Z, John, John, Paul, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 9)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 13-14)
- Howard, John, John, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 10)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 15-16)
- Craig Rose and John Gordon, February 19, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 11)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 17-18)
- Morty, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 12)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 19)
- Charlie, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 13)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 20)
- Racism Sum-Up, March 21, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 14 A-B)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 21-23)
- Black drivers on racism, April 11, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 15)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 24-25)
- Dover Discussion, February 7, 1978
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 16 A-C)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 26-31)
- Activists, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 17)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 32)
- Old Timers, September 15, 1976
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 18)
  - Access CDs (Box 1, Cd 33-34)
- Joe Napola, undated
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 19)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 35)
- Owner Driver Unity Meet, June 6, 1972
  - Original audio recording (Box Shared Tamiment 103, Cassette 20)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd 36)